Guide to the Alexander Gumby Collection of Negroiana,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Alexander Gumby Collection of Negroiana,
[ca. 1800]-1981
Gumby, L. S. Alexander, 1885-1961, comp.
ca. 5,000 items (17 boxes, 161 v., 1 oversize folder)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library,
MS#0527
4078845
Biographical Note
Born Feb. 1, 1885, in Maryland, Gumby was the son of Evangelist Levi Thomas and Louisa Morris Gumby. In 1901, he and his sister were sent to live with their grandparents and there the young man who loved reading made his first scrapbook at the age of 16 with some old wallpaper and a paste of flour and water. Gumby's first clippings were of President McKinley's assassination in Sept. 1901.
He spent the next year at Dover State College in Delaware studying law to fulfill his grandmother's dream for him. But he became impatient and felt his skills were inadequate. He packed his scrapbooks and eventually headed to New York City, where he immediately fell in love with the place that would be his home until his death almost 60 years later.
"At once I became a New Yorker in spirit and principle for I found here more freedom of action than I had ever known before," Gumby wrote in his 1951 essay, "The Adventures of My Scrapbook," for the Columbia Library World. Gumby became an enthusiastic fan of theatre and art and "formed the habit" of collecting all the playbills, pictures, and clippings he could find of his favorites.
During those early years in New York, Gumby wrote that it seemed "a willingness to change jobs was a mark of a youth's ambition." A friend told him of a job as a waiter at Columbia and there he began his relationships with a number of professors and students. He also clipped "everything I could find" about popular professors and President Nicholas Murry Butler.
By 1910, he organized his clippings and began to take his role more seriously. Gumby studied other collections in libraries across the U.S. and Canada, and also began collecting rare book editions and manuscripts with the help of his wealthy friend who was a partner in a Wall Street firm. And he met with other collectors like Arturo Schomburg.
At the same time, Gumby took a variety of other jobs to help sustain his passion. He became, for instance, the personal butler of a wealthy banker in the same area now known as Riverdale's Wave Hill. Gumby also was a founding member of the Southern Utopia Fraternity, a group organized for "young men from the South who came to New York seeking a larger experience."
Soon he became better known more for his collection of rare editions than for his scrapbooks and he opened the Gumby Book Studio at 2144 Fifth Avenue between 131st and 132nd Streets in Harlem. The historian lined his studio with books and continued clipping and pasting historic documents in his scrapbooks. Gumby's Studio grew so popular that it became a gathering place for many artists, actors, musicians, intellectuals, gays and lesbians of the Harlem Renaissance. Gumby called it the first "unpremeditated interracial movement in Harlem."
Meanwhile, Gumby's reputation as "The Count" and "Mr. Scrapbook" also continued to grow and he was asked to exhibit his collections in cities along the East Coast, earning him a listing in the 1922 edition of the Private Book Collectors' Who's Who. But by the Crash of 1929, Gumby's wealthy friend lost millions and the Studio lost support of its regulars. The collapse took such a toll on Gumby that he was forced to give up the Studio, sell many of his editions, and store his scrapbooks in the cellar of an acquaintance's house.
"The loss of my studio and fatigue from overwork," he wrote, sent Gumby first to Riverside Hospital in the Bronx and then to Randall's Island Hospital where he spent the next four years. In both hospitals, though, he continued collecting newspaper articles (some about his own hospitalization), photographs of visiting friends, and get well cards, all of which are included in his six autobiographical scrapbooks.
When he was released in 1934, Gumby set about retrieving his collections and restoring their condition, all the time adding more and more clippings, autographs and other documents. By 1950 he gave his collection to Columbia and in 1951, the University hired him for eight months to organize the materials.
Alexander Gumby considered his "History of the Negro in Scrapbook" more than a hobby. He wrote that, "The collection could well be called 'The Unwritten History.'" Gumby concentrated on African American history primarily because, "There are so many surprising and startling historical events pertaining to, or relating to the American Negro that are not recorded in the Standard Histories, dictionaries and school text-books, or if so, they are shaded so that they sound like a Ripley's 'Believe It or Not.' "
From "Black History Remains Alive in Alexander Gumby's Popular Scrapbooks" By Jo Kadlecek. Columbia News. Published: Feb 18, 2002.
Scope and Content
A collection concerned with the various phases of black life in America, containing clippings, pamphlets, photographs, pictures, extracts from periodicals, and a representative group of approximately 350 letters, signatures, manuscripts, and documents. Among the letters are several each from Countee Cullen, Frederick Douglass, Alexander Dumas, fils, William Lloyd Garrison, Claude McKay, Abraham Lincoln, Henry Mencken, William Pickens, Albert A. Smith, and Booker T. Washington. Also, eighteen slavery documents.
Most of the material is mounted in 161 scrapbooks or groups of folio leaves. The clippings are from both general and specialized newspapers and magazines ranging in date from 1850 to 1960, however the majority of the material falls between 1910 and 1950. Whole volumes are devoted to major figures such as Joe Louis, Booker T. Washington, Paul Robeson, and Josephine Baker. Four scrapbooks contain signatures, signed photographs, and letters from a great variety of individuals. Among the unnumbered volumes of personal scrapbooks there are six volumes labeled "Gumby's Autobiography" containing personal letters, calling cards, photographs, post cards, and other printed material relating to Gumby's life.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 5 series:
Series I: Letters, Manuscripts, Documents, and Art
Series II: Autographs and Photographs
Series III: Scrapbooks
Part IV: Subjects
Part V: Additions
Subjects
Baker, Josephine, 1906-1975.; Cullen, Countee, 1903-1946.; Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895.; Dumas, Alexandre, 1824-1895.; Garrison, William Lloyd, 1805-1879.; Joplin, Scott, 1868-1917.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; Louis, Joe, 1914-1981.; McKay, Claude, 1890-1948.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Pickens, William, 1881-1954.; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976.; Smith, Albert Alex.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.; United States--History.; United States--Social conditions.; United States--Social life and customs.; African American athletes.; African American scientists.; African American teachers.; African American women.; African Americans.; African Americans--History.; African Americans--Social conditions.; African Americans in the performing arts.; Slavery--United States.; Autographs.; Bibliographies.; Brochures.; Galley proofs.; Greeting cards.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Poems.; Postcards.; Programs.; Releases.; Scores.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.; Visiting cards.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1951 M-51 Gumby, L. S. Alexander Gift
1982 M-1982 Scott Joplin items Solomon, Joseph Gift
Alternate Formats
Part I: Letters, manuscripts, doucments (2 boxes) is on microfilm.
Microfilm available for scrapbooks 1-139.
Unnumbered scrapbook: Autobiography... (5 vols.) is on microfilm.
Unnumbered scrapbook: Autographs (4 vols.) is on microfilm.
Gumby collected this material during the first half of the 20th century.
Gift of L.S.A. Gumby, 1951-1960.
Gift of Joseph Solomon, 1982.
- Series 1: Letters, Manuscripts, Documents, and Art
  - Subseries I.1: Letters, Manuscripts, and Documents
    - Cataloged letters and manuscripts: Slavery documents -- Miscellaneous uncalaloged letters -- Holograph drafts and final typescripts of Gumby's own letters, (2 boxes, ) (Box A & B)
      [Available on microfilm # 96-2040 and 96-2041]
  - Subseries I.2: Art
    - Argudin, P. Portrait of Alexander Gumby, [New York], 1934, (22 x 19 inches Pastel, 1 folder, ) (Box 189)
    - Artist's Pallette, signed by numerous friends, 1934-1938 (Box 19)
- Series II: Autographs and Photographs
  - Signatures, signed photographs, and letters., (4 volumes in 2 Flat Boxes ) (Box 125 & 126)
    [Not on Microfilm.]
- Series III: Scrapbooks
  - Numbered Scrapbooks
    - Adventures, (1 volume, ) (Box 127, Folder 1)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 1.]
    - Amalgamation of races, (2 volumes) (Box 127, Folder 2 to 3)
    - Art, (2 volumes volumes, ) (Box 128, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Art, Modern, (1 volume, ) (Box 128, Folder 6)
    - Art, Negro, (1 volume, ) (Box 128, Folder 7)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 2.]
    - Baker, Josephine, (1 volume, ) (Box Volume 8)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 2. Volume missing as of 2/2000 [PL]
    - Basketball, (1 volume, ) (Box 129, Folder 9)
    - Book reviews, (2 volumes) (Box 129, Folder 10 to 11)
    - Breaking the bonds of slavery, (2 volumes, ) (Box 130, Folder 12 to 13)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 2 & 3.]
    - Bunche, Ralph, (1 volume, ) (Box 131, Folder 14)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 3.]
    - Carver, George Washington, (1 volume, ) (Box 131, Folder 15)
    - Catholics, (1 volume, ) (Box 131, Folder 16)
    - Classic art, (1 volume, ) (Box 131, Folder 17)
    - Charles, Eggard and Joe Woolcott, (1 volume, ) (Box 132, Folder 18)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 4.]
    - Cole and Johnson, and Will Marion, (1 volume, ) (Box 132, Folder 19)
    - Columbia University, (1 volume, ) (Box 132, Folder 20)
    - Cullen, Countee, (1 volume, ) (Box 133, Folder 21)
    - Dancers, (2 volumes, ) (Box 133, Folder 22 to 23)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 5.]
    - Douglass, Frederick, (1 volume, ) (Box 134, Folder 24)
    - Du Bois, W. E. B., (1 volume, ) (Box Volume 25 in Flat 134, Folder 25)
    - Dunbar, Laurence, (1 volume, ) (Box 134, Folder 26)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 6.]
    - Education North and South, (1 volume, ) (Box 135, Folder 27)
    - Ethiopia, (2 volumes, ) (Box 135 & 136, Folder 28 to 29)
      [Available on Microfilm Reels 6 and 7.]
    - Father Divine, (1 volume, ) (Box 136, Folder 30)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 7.]
    - Football, (1 volume, ) (Box 136, Folder 31)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 8.]
    - Garvy, Marcus, (1 volume, ) (Box 137, Folder 32)
    - Green Pastures, (1 volume, ) (Box 137, Folder 33)
    - Greenwich Village, (1 volume, ) (Box 137, Folder 34)
    - Gumby Book Studio, (2 volumes, ) (Box Box138, Folder 35 to 36)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 9]
    - Gumby Book Studio: Quarterly, (1 volume, Galley Proofs, ) (Box 15, Folder 37)
    - Gumby Book Studio: Guest Book, (1 volume, ) (Box 15, Folder 38)
    - Haiti, (1 volume, ) (Box 139, Folder 39)
    - Harlem, (2 volumes, ) (Box 139 & 140, Folder 40 to 41)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 10.]
    - Hayes, Roland and Marian Anderson, (1 volume, ) (Box 140, Folder 42)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 11.]
    - Hughes, Langston, (1 volume, ) (Box 141, Folder 43)
    - Hunter, Morris, (1 volume, ) (Box 141, Folder 44)
    - Inter-marriage of Negros and Whites, (2 volumes, ) (Box 141, Folder 45 to 46)
    - Jazz, (2 volumes, ) (Box 142, Folder 47 to 48)
    - Jewish-Prophet-Others, (1 volume, ) (Box 142, Folder 49)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 12.]
    - Johnson, Jack, (1 volume, ) (Box 142, Folder 50)
    - Lafayette Theatre, (1 volume, ) (Box 143, Folder 51)
    - Libraries, (1 volume, ) (Box 143, Folder 52)
    - Little Theaters, (2 volumes, ) (Box 143, Folder 53 to 54)
    - Louis, Joe, (8 volumes, ) (Box 144 & 145, Folder 55 to 63)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 12 & 13.]
    - Lynchings and Race Riots, (2 volumes, ) (Box 146, Folder 64 to 65)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 13.]
    - Mills, Florence, (1 volume, ) (Box 146, Folder 66)
    - Moving Pictures, (2 volumes, ) (Box 147, Folder 67 to 68)
    - Music, (3 volumes, ) (Box 147 & 148, Folder 69, 70 and 70a)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 13 & 14.]
    - NAACP, (2 volumes, ) (Box 148, Folder 71 to 72)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 14.]
    - Negro and Communism, (1 volume, ) (Box 148, Folder 73)
    - Negro as a Soldier, (4 volumes, ) (Box 149 & 150, Folder 74 to 77)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 14 & 15.]
    - Negro Business, Labor, and Newspapers, (1 volume, ) (Box 150, Folder 78)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 15.]
    - Negro Columnists, (2 volumes, ) (Box 151, Folder 79 to 80)
    - Negro Entertainers, (1 volume, ) (Box 151, Folder 81)
    - Negro Fighters, (4 volumes, ) (Box 152 & 153, Folder 82 to 85)
    - Negro in Africa, (2 volumes, ) (Box 154, Folder 86 to 87)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 16.]
    - Negro in Baseball, (1 volume, ) (Box 154, Folder 88)
    - Negro in Bondage, (1 volume, ) (Box 155, Folder 89)
    - Negro in Congress, (1 volume, ) (Box 156, Folder 90)
    - Negro in Drama, (4 volumes, ) (Box 156 & 157, Folder 91 to 94)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 16 & 17.]
    - Negro in Politics, (2 volumes, ) (Box 157, Folder 95 to 96)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 17.]
    - Negro in Stamps, (1 volume, ) (Box 158, Folder 97)
    - Negro Musicals on Broadway, (2 volumes, ) (Box 157 & 159, Folder 98 to 99)
    - Negro Poets, (2 volumes, ) (Box 159 & 160, Folder 100 to 101)
    - Negro Religions, (1 volume, ) (Box 160, Folder 102)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 18.]
    - Negro Schools, (2 volumes, ) (Box 160, Folder 103 to 104)
    - Negro Sports, (1 volume, ) (Box 161, Folder 105)
    - Olympic Games, (1 volume, ) (Box 161, Folder 106)
    - Opera, (1 volume, ) (Box 162, Folder 107)
    - Pickens, William, (1 volume, ) (Box 162, Folder 108)
    - Porgy, (1 volume, ) (Box 163, Folder 109)
    - Protestantantism, (1 volume, ) (Box 163, Folder 110)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 19.]
    - Radio and Television, (1 volume, ) (Box 163, Folder 111)
    - Robeson, Paul, (1 volume, ) (Box 175, Folder 112)
    - Robinson, Jackie, (2 volumes, ) (Box 163, Folder 113 to 114)
    - Robinson, Sugar Ray, (1 volume, ) (Box 177, Folder 115)
    - Rogers, J. A., (1 volume, ) (Box 177, Folder 116)
    - Shakespeare, William, (1 volume, ) (Box 178, Folder 117)
    - Social Equality, (4 volumes, ) (Box 178, 179 & 180, Folder 118 to 121)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 19 & 20.]
    - South, (4 volumes, ) (Box 180, 181 & 182, Folder 122 to 125)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 20.]
    - Supreme Court and the Negro, (1 volume, ) (Box 185, Folder 126)
    - They Broke Through Discrimination, (1 volume, ) (Box 186, Folder 127)
    - Thurman, Wallace, Jean Toomer and Claude McKay, (1 volume, ) (Box 186, Folder 128)
    - Urban League, (1 volume, ) (Box 186, Folder 129)
    - Washington, Booker T., (3 volumes, ) (Box 186 & 187, Folder 130 to 132)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 21.]
    - Waters, Ethel, (1 volume, ) (Box 187, Folder 133)
    - Wipper, Leigh, (1 volume, ) (Box 188, Folder 134)
    - White Fighters, (1 volume, ) (Box 188, Folder 135)
    - Williams and Walker, (1 volume, ) (Box 189, Folder 136)
    - Johnson, James W., (1 volume, ) (Box 188, Folder 137)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 22.]
    - Mencken, Henry L., (1 volume, ) (Box 189, Folder 138)
    - Miscellaneous, (1 volume, ) (Box 189, Folder 139)
    - Greeting and Christmas Cards, (2 volumes, ) (Box 16, Folder 140 to 141)
    - Stamp Scrapbook, (1 volume, ) (Box 17, Folder 142)
    - Tony P. [Gumby's cat], (1 volume, ) (Box 18, Folder 143)
    - Poetry, (1 volume, ) (Box 190, Folder 144)
    - Odd, Strange and Curious, (1 volume, ) (Box 190, Folder 145)
    - Art, (1 volume, ) (Box 191, Folder 146)
    - Literature, (1 volume, ) (Box 191, Folder 147)
    - Stewart, James, (2 volumes, ) (Box 18 & 19, Folder 148 to 149)
    - Sinatra, Frank, (1 volume, ) (Box 20, Folder 150)
    - Movie Stars, (1 volume, ) (Box 20, Folder 151)
  - Gumby's Autobiography In Scrapbooks
    Volumes 1 & 2 [in one volume] are missing. They were microfilmed and are on microfilm 96-2042.
    - Gumby's Autobiography In Scrapbooks: Number 3, (1 Volume, ) (Box 21)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 95-2042. [The target on the microfilm label this as "Volume 2"]
    - Gumby's Autobiography In Scrapbooks: Number 4, (1 volume, ) (Box 22)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 96-2042. [The target on the microfilm label this as "Volume 3"]
    - Gumby's Autobiography In Scrapbooks: Number 5, (1 volume, ) (Box 23)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 96-2043. [The target on the microfilm label this as "Volume 4"]
    - Gumby's Autobiography In Scrapbooks: Number 6, (1 volume, ) (Box 24)
      [Available on Microfilm Reel 96-2043. [The target on the microfilm label this as "volume 5"]
- Part IV: Subjects
  - Africa (Box 1)
  - Africa - The Congo (Box 1)
  - Africa - East Africa (Box 1)
    [Scrapbook compiled by James Arthur Hutton, Manchester, England]
  - Africa - Stamps (Box 1)
  - Africa - Union of South Africa (Box 1)
  - Alabama (Box 2)
  - British Race Relations (Box 2)
  - Cartoons (Box 2)
  - Civil Rights (Box 2)
  - Civil Rights Bill (Box 2)
  - Communism (Box 2)
  - Crimes - News Clippings (Box 3)
  - Crimes - The Virginus Outrage (Box 3)
  - Crimes - Claraence Darrow (Box 3)
  - Crimes - French - Petain (Box 3)
  - Crimes - The Munn Trial (Box 3)
  - Curtwright, Arthur (Box 3)
  - Darden, Norman (Box 3)
  - Death Notices (Box 3)
  - Delaware (Box 3)
  - Discrimination (Box 3)
  - Education (Box 3)
  - Educators (Box 3)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight (Box 3)
  - Ethopia (Box 3)
  - Father Divine (Box 4)
  - Films (Box 4)
  - Florida (Box 4)
  - Gibson, Althea (Box 4)
  - Haiti (Box 4)
  - Harlem (Box 4)
  - Henson, Matthew (Box 4)
  - History (Box 4)
  - Housing (Box 4)
  - Hughes, Langston (Box 4)
  - Illinois (Box 5)
  - Integration (Box 5)
  - Inter-Racial Marriage (Box 5)
  - Invitations (Box 5)
  - Jack, Hulan E. (Box 5)
  - Jackman, Harold (Box 5)
  - Kennedy, John and Robert (Box 5)
  - Kentucky (Box 5)
  - King, Martin Luther (Box 5)
  - Korean War (Box 5)
  - Labor (Box 6)
  - Labor - Negro Actors Guild (Box 6)
  - Letters to the New York Times (Box 6)
  - Liberia (Box 6)
  - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 6)
  - Literature (Box 6)
  - Little Rock - 1957 (Box 6)
  - Little Rock - 1958 (Box 6)
  - Little Rock - 1959 (Box 6)
  - Louisiana (Box 6)
  - Lucy Case (Box 6)
  - Marshall, Charles (Box 7)
  - Milestones (Box 7)
  - Mississippi (Box 7)
  - Music (Box 7)
  - Music - Carnegie Hall (Box 7)
  - Music - Times Hall (Box 7)
  - Music - Town Hall (Box 7)
  - NAACP (Box 8)
  - Negro as Soldier (Box 8)
  - New Jersey (Box 8)
  - New York City Hospital (Box 8)
  - North Carolina (Box 8)
  - Nugent, R. Bruce (Box 8)
  - Opera (Box 8)
  - Painters (Box 8)
  - Patton, General George S (Box 8)
  - Personal Friends (Box 8)
  - Personal Records (Box 8)
  - Physicians (Box 9)
  - Pictures (Box 9)
  - Politics (Box 9)
  - Powell, Adam Clayton (Box 9)
  - Prack, Tony (Box 9)
  - Religion (Box 9)
  - Robeson, Paul (Box 9)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Box 10)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore (Box 10)
  - Royalty (Box 10)
  - Science (Box 10)
  - Segregation (Box 10)
  - Sale of a Negro Woman, 1777, (1 Signed Bill of Sale, ) (Box 10)
  - Slavery (Box 10)
  - The South (Box 10)
  - South Carolina (Box 10)
  - Sports - Baseball (Box 11)
  - Sports - Boxing, Track, Football, Basketball (Box 11)
  - Sports - Campenella, Roy (Box 12)
  - Sports - Louis, Joe (Box 12)
  - Sports - Patterson, Floyd (Box 12)
  - Sports - Robinson, Jackie (Box 12)
  - Sports - Robinson, Suagr Ray (Box 12)
  - Supreme Court (Box 12)
  - Theatre (Box 13)
  - Theatre - "Change Your Luck" (Box 13)
  - Theatre - Critics (Box 13)
  - Theatre - "The Green Pastures" (Box 13)
  - Theatre - Negro Players in the Casts of White Shows (Box 13)
  - Theatre - The Palybill, 1937-1949 (Box 13)
  - Theatre - The Palybill, 1950-1959 (Box 13)
  - Theatre - "Porgy" (Box 13)
  - Theatre - "St. Louis Woman" (Box 13)
  - Tuskegee Institute (Box 13)
  - The Unknown Soldier (Box 13)
  - Urban League (Box 13)
  - Whipper, Leigh (Box 13)
  - Worthy, William D. (Box 13)
  - Notebooks (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
- Part V: Additions
  - Scott Joplin
    - Correspondence and documents relating to Joplin bibliography: Works copyrighted by Joplin -- Memoribilia (with related correspondence) -- Pulitzer Prize, 1976 -- Entertainment Hall of Fame, 1975 -- Printed ephemera (programs, press releases, brochures) -- Printed materials (clippings) -- Printed materials (musical scores) (Box 25)
      [Gift of Joseph Solomon, 1982]
    - "Tremonisha" (original cast recording). "Tremonisha" (musical score: 1 page for Act III), (1 folder, ) (Box 188)